suppose we have a right triangle with
legs of length A and B and a hypotenuse
of C we can draw an A by a square off
the side of length a we can draw a b by
b square off the side of length B and we
can draw a c by C Square Off the
hypotenuse though we leave the C by C
Square unshaded the total shaded area in
this diagram is a^2 + b^2 let's perform
a few area preserving Transformations
first we Shear each of the two squares
along the opposite side of the triangle
we rotate these sheared regions and then
we Shear them down again filling the C
by C Square since shearing and rotating
doesn't affect the area we see that a^2
+ b^2 must equal to c^2 so here we have
a visual proof of the Pythagorean
theorem which says that the sum of the
squares of the legs of a right triangle
must equal the square of the hypotenuse